Eshwen Bhal

DATA SCIENTIST

22 Rownham Court, Rownham Mead, Bristol, United Kingdom. BS8 4YE

🛮 +44 (0) 78414 09961 | 💌 milanman.eshb@gmail.com | 🖸 eshwen | 🛅 eshwen-bhal-phd-714557195

Profile

I am a data scientist working on alternative data sources for the Consumer Price Index, focusing on web scraping. I have recently completed a PhD in particle physics, searching for dark matter using big data from the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) as part of the CMS experiment at CERN. This involves statistical analysis of large datasets with expertise in Python, and solving wide ranging problems from physics standpoints to programming challenges. Additional responsibilities have included providing detector-related expertise and software, teaching undergraduates and doing public outreach. Aside from work, I partake in many activities such as taekwondo, weight lifting, hiking and skiing.

Education

University of Bristol

Bristol, United Kingdom

DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY IN PHYSICS

2016 - 2021

- Thesis: Searches for dark matter with a focus on invisibly decaying Higgs bosons using the full Run-2 dataset of the CMS experiment at the LHC *Under supervision of H. Flächer*
 - Explored various physics models in search of dark matter by analysing data from LHC's CMS experiment. Set **world leading limits** on Higgs boson decay to invisible states.
 - Executed robust, comprehensive statistical analysis with hypothesis testing on real and simulated data, meticulously documenting concepts, results and code.
 - Composed robust, efficient code to simulate data and perform each step of analysis. Written predominantly in Python, leveraging modern data science tools, vectorisation, and distributed computing to process multiple terabytes of data.
- Postgraduate student representative for particle physics, 2019–20 Role in Student-Staff Liaison Committee
- Long term attachment at world's largest particle physics laboratory CERN 18 month placement abroad in Switzerland
- Calorimeter Layer-2 on call expert and Level-1 Trigger shifter Additional responsibilities with CERN
 - Assisted in detector operations and monitoring so CMS experiment could take data efficiently and operate smoothly.
 - Developed and deployed software for subsystem of Level-1 Trigger to apply corrections and calibrations to data on the fly.

University of Exeter

Exeter, United Kingdom

MASTER OF PHYSICS WITH HONOURS IN PHYSICS WITH ASTROPHYSICS

2012 - 2016

- Grade: First Class 77 % overall mark (4.0 GPA equivalent)
- Dissertation: **Simulations of Exoplanet Light Curves** *Under supervision of T. Harries*
 - Developed software in C to simulate photons interacting simple planetary atmospheres, producing light curves akin to data from telescopes. Visualised model planets with maps of density and composition.
 - Able to model more complex atmospheres for comparison to real exoplanets to infer their composition.
 - Utilised Monte Carlo random sampling for scattering of photons, and parallelisation to efficiently run the code over millions of them.

Monmouth Comprehensive School

Monmouth, United Kingdom

SECONDARY SCHOOL QUALIFICATIONS

2005 - 2012

- A Level, $2010-12 A^*A^*B$ in Mathematics, Biology, and Physics. Chemistry AS Level with grade B
- **Open University**, 2011–12 *Introducing Astronomy (10 credit course)*
- GCSE, 2008–10 10 including English Language and Mathematics at grades A* (4) and A (6)

Experience

Office for National Statistics

Newport, United Kingdom

DATA SCIENTIST 2021 – Present

• Web scraping products and prices from various retailers to assist in creating a more accurate Consumer Price Index.

• Building spiders in Python to reliably scrape websites, then store and clean data for further analysis.

University of Bristol

Bristol, United Kingdom

COMPUTATIONAL PHYSICS TUTOR

2019 - 2020

• Taught programming in Python to third year undergraduate students, with applications for numerically solving physics problems with numpy and visualisation with matplotlib. Formally marked assignments and provided feedback.

Skills _____

Data analysis

- Primary focus of my PhD concerns statistical analysis of large (multi-terabyte) datasets collected by the CMS experiment from the Large Hadron Collider.
- Developed analysis software for dark matter searches and detector-effect calibrations in Python and C++, using modern data science tools such as numpy and pandas, and parallel programming on computing grids.
- Visualisation with ROOT and matplotlib. Formal presentations of results with LaTeX and Microsoft PowerPoint.

Collaboration

• Belonging to, and working alongside, several groups of around a dozen people as well as a global research collaboration of over 4,000 people.

Problem solving

• Principal component of any physics degree. As an undergraduate, conducted more traditional pen-and-paper problem solving in many topics. As a PhD student, wrote code to solve physics problems numerically and perform data analysis for high energy particle physics.

Multitasking

• Often working on multiple projects at once with different people during PhD. These have included data analysis, software-implemented calibrations to data from detector effects, and expertise and shift work for subsystems of the detector.

Communication

- Presented formally in my PhD at all levels: regular working group updates, research group and collaboration-wide talks, and several conference posters and talks.
- Participated in outreach to the public at the CERN Open Days 2019 and at @Bristol.

Awards _____

2016	Dean's Commendation , in recognition of outstanding achievement in my fourth year	University of Exeter
2015	Physics Award, for being one of the three students with the highest marks in my third year	University of Exeter
2014	Dean's Commendation , in recognition of outstanding achievement in my second year	University of Exeter
2013	Physics Award , for being one of the three students with the highest marks in my first year	University of Exeter
2013	Dean's Commendation, in recognition of outstanding achievement in my first year	University of Exeter